Peter! What do you think you're doing?
彼得 你在干什么呢 ?
Peter, quickly, the shelter. Now!
彼得 快进防空洞 快点
- Come on! - Wait...
快点 等等…
Come on, leave it!
快点 快走
Mommy!
妈味
Lucy, come on!
露西 快走
- Come on, quickly! - Run!
快点 快 快跑
- Hurry! - Mum!
快点 妈妈
- Wait! Dad! - Ed!
等等 和区和多
- Edmund, no! - I'll get him!
爱德蒙 不要
- Peter, come back! - Ed! Come here!
彼得 回来
Edmund! Get down!
爱德蒙 四下
Come on, you idiot, run!
快点 你这个和白痪 快跑
Get out!
快出去
Come on!
快点
Why can't you think of anyone but yourself? You're so selfish!
你为什么不替别人想一想 ? 你太自私了
- You could've got us killed! - Stop it!
你差点害死我们大家 别说了
It's OK.
没事了
Why can't you just do as you're told?
你为什么就是不背乖乖听话 ?
Alms for the poor. Alms for the poor.
施舍点东西吧…
God bless you, sir.
上帝保佑你 先生
Children and evacuation staff...
儿童和搬离工作人 员…
You need to keep this on, darling. All right?
亲爱的 你得戴上这个
You warm enough? Good girl.
你穿的够暖和吗 ? 好孩子
Say hello to Auntie Laura. Goodbye, darling, we love you.
帮我向劳拉阿姨问好 再见 亲爱的 我们爱你
it'd mean the war was over. We wouldn't have to.
那就表示战争已经结束 我们就用不着离开了
You will listen to your brother, won't you, Edmund?
爱德蒙 你会听哥哥的话吧?
Promise me you'll look after the others.
答应我你会照顾好其他人
I will, Mum.
我会的 妈妈
- Good man. - All aboard! All aboard!
好孩子 所有乘客请上车…
- Bye, darling! - Bye!
再见 亲爱的 再见
Susan.
苏表
Be a big girl.
要像个大姑娘
Hold on to your brother's hand. Don't let it go.
抓紧哥哥的手 别松开
All right. Off you go.
好了 你们上车吧
- All aboard! - Bye-bye. Love you.
所有和磁客请上车 再见 我爱你们
Hey, get off. I know how to get on a train by myself.
嘿 放手 我自己会上火车
Get off me!
放开我
May I have your tickets, please? Tickets, please.
我能看一下你的票吗 ? 请让我看一下村
Peter.
彼得
- That's right. On you go. - Yes. Thank you.
请上车吧 好 谢诈
Come along. Come along this way, please.
这边 请往这边走
Come on, Lucy. We have to stick together now.
过来 露西 我们别走散了
Everything's gonna be all right. It's gonna be fine.
一切都会好起来的 会好起来的
Bye, Mommy! I love you!
再见 妈妈 我爱你
- Bye-bye, dear. - Bye! We'll miss you! See you soon.
再见 亲爱的 再见 我们会想你的 再见了
- Llove you, Mum! Bye! - See you soon!
我爱你 妈妈 再见 再见了
- Write to us, Mum! - Love you!
给我们写信 妈妈 爱你
Goosey Station. Goosey Station.
去西站到了…-
Give me your hand. Let's get going.
把手给我 我们下去吧
The professor knew we were coming.
教授知道我们要来的
Perhaps we've been incorrectly labeled.
也许我们挂错标牌了
Come on, hup!
快点 轰
And whoa. Whoa.
吓…-
- Mrs. Macready? - I'm afraid so.
是麦瑞东太太吗?
Is this it, then? Haven't you brought anything else?
就是这些吗 ? 你们没有带别的东西 ?
No, ma'am.
没有 太太
It's just us.
就我们四个
Small favors.
省了我一点麻烦
Come on. Good girl. Come on. Come on.
快点 好马儿 快点…
Professor Kirke is not accustomed to havin' children in this house.
冠克教授不太习惯 屋子里出现孩子
And, as such, there are a few rules we need to follow.
因此 有元项规纸必须遵守
There will no shoutin’.
不准喊叫
Or runnin’. No improper use of the dumbwaiter.
不准奔跑 不准乱动送货的升降机
No touchin' of the historical artifacts!
不准乱摸吉董
And above all,
最重要的是
there shall be no disturbin' of the professor.
不准打扰到教授
German aircraft carried out a number of attacks on Great Britain last night.
德军飞机于昨晚对英国 发动了一系列空缆
The raids, which lasted for several hours...
此欢空克持续了数小时之久…
The sheets feel scratchy.
床单好扎人
Wars don't last forever, Lucy. We'll be home soon.
战争不是永远的 露西 我们很快就会回家的
- Yeah, if home's still there. - Isn't it time you were in bed?
对 如果家还在的话 你是不是该瞧觉了 ?
- Yes, Mum. - Ed!
遵命 老妈 爱德!
You saw outside. This place is huge.
你在外面也看到了 这地方很大
We can do whatever we want here.
我们想干什么都行
Tomorrow's going to be great.
明天会是美好的一天
"Gastrovascular."
Gastrovascular
Come on, Peter. Gastrovascular.
快点 彼得 Gastrovascular
- Is it Latin? - Yes.
这是不是拉于语? 是的
Is it Latin for "worst game ever invented"?
它的意思是不是 「 最无聊的游戏上」 ?
We could play hide and seek.
我们可以玩捉迷城
But we're already having so much fun.
可我们玩的正开心呢
Come on, Peter, please.
来吧 彼得 拜托
Pretty please?
求求你啦
- One, two, three, four, - What?
1234… 什么 ?
five, six, seven, eight,
5678…
nine, ten, 11...
9 10 11…
24, 25, 26...
.24 25 26…-
I was here first!
是我先到这几的
..15, 76, 77, 78, 79, 80,
5 76 77 78 79 80…
81, 82, 83, 84,
81 82 83 84…-
85, 86, 85, 86, 87, 88,
885 86 87 88…
89, 90, 91, 92,
89 90 91 92
93, 94, 95...
93 94 95…-
Were you hiding from me?
你是在躲着我吗 ?
No.
不是的
Well...
呢…-
I just... L..
我只是…我…
No. No. I just...
不 我只是…
I was just... I didn't want to scare you.
我只是…我不想吓着你
If you don't mind my asking... what are you?
请别介意我这么问 你是什么 ?
Well, I'ma... Well, I'm a faun.
呢 我是…我是人羊
And what about you?
你呢 ?
You must be some kind of beardless dwarf?
你肯定是没有长毛的侏儒吧 ?
I'm not a dwarf! I'm a girl!
我才不是侏儒 我是个女孩
And, actually, I'm tallest in my class.
而且我是我们班最高的
You mean to say that you're a Daughter of Eve?
你是说你是夏娃的女儿 ?
Well, my mum's name is Helen.
我妈妈的名字叫海伦
Yes, but you are in fact human.
对 可你确实是个人类
Yes, of course.
对 当然了
What are you doing here?
你来这几和干什么 ?
Well, l was hiding in the wardrobe in the spare room, and...
我正躲在空房间的衣橱里 结果…-
Spare Oom? Is that in Narnia?
空皇疆 ? 这地方属于纳尼亚吗?
Narnia? What's that?
纳尼亚?那是什么 ?
Well, dear girl, you're in it.
孩子 这几就是纳尼亚的国土
Everything from the lamppost
从那个灯柱一直到
all the way to Castle Cair Paravel on the Eastern Ocean,
东海边上的凯尔帕拉瓦大城堡
every stick and stone you see,
你所看到的每条树枝每块石头
every icicle is Narnia.
每个冰柱 都属于纳尼亚
This is an awfully big wardrobe.
这个衣柱真是大得惊人啊
War Drobe? I'm sorry.
衣橱 ? 对不起
Please allow me to introduce myself. My name is Tumnus.
请容许我做一下自我介绍 我的名字叫吐纳思
Pleased to meet you, Mr. Tumnus. I'm Lucy Pevensie.
很高兴认识你 旺纳思先生 我叫露西派文西
- Oh, you shake it. - Why?
哦 你应该握握我的手 为什么 ?
I... [don't know.
我…我也不知道
People do it when they meet each other.
人们见面的时候都会这么做
Well, then, Lucy Pevensie from the shining city of War Drobe
好吧 来自奇妙的空皇强王国
in the wondrous land of Spare Oom,
…那光明的衣橱之城的 露西派文西
how would it be if you came and had tea with me?
你愿意跟我一起喝杯茶吗 ?
Well, thank you very much, but I...
谢谢你 可是我…
I probably should be getting back.
我该回去了
It's only just around the corner. And there'll be a glorious fire
只要转个弯就到了 里面生着很旺的炉火
with toast and tea and cakes.
还有面包 茶水和有蛋薰
And, perhaps, we'll even break into the sardines.
甚至还能吃点沙丁鱼
- [don't know. - Come on.
我真的不知道 来吧
It's not every day that I get to make a new friend.
我并不是每天都能交到新朋友
Well, l suppose I could come for a little while.
我想我可以坐上一小会几
If you have sardines.
如果你有沙丁鱼的话
By the bucketload.
有一大桶呢
You all right?
你还好吧 ?
Well, here we are.
我们到了
Come along.
进来吧
- After you. - May I help you with that?
你先请 我来帮你拿吧
Thank you very much.
谢谢你
He has a nice face.
他长得很籼
He looks a lot like you.
跟你很像
No.
不
No, I'm not very much like him at all, really.
我其实一点都不像他 真的
My father's fighting in the war.
我父亲现在正在打侈
My father went away to war too.
我父亲也到远方打仗去了
But that was a long, long time ago.
不过那是很久很久以前的事了
- Before this dreadful winter. - Winter's not all bad.
在这个可怕的冬天来临之前 冬天也没那么糟糙啦
There's ice skating and snowball fights.
可以渭冰 还可以打才会
- And Christmas! - Not here.
还有圣诞节 这里没有圣诞节
No. No, we haven't had a Christmas in a hundred years.
我们已经有一百年 没有过圣诞节了
What? No presents for a hundred years?
什么 ? 一百年没有收到礼物了 ?
Always winter, never Christmas.
一直都是冬天 却从来没有圣诞节
It's been a long winter.
这是一个漫长的冬天
But you would have loved Narnia . In summer.
但你一定会喜欢上 夏天的纳尼亚
We fauns danced with the dryads all night,
我们人羊会跟树精整夜跳舞
and, you know, we never got tired.
而且我们从来都不疲供
And music. Oh, such music!
还有音乐 哦 美妙的音乐
Would... would you like to hear some now?
你…你想听点音乐吗 ?
Yes, please.
好的
Now, are you familiar
你元悉…
- with any Narnian lullabies? - Sorry, no.
…纳尼亚的催眠曲吗 ? 对不起 不熟悉
Well, that's good.
哦 很好
Because this... probably won't sound anything like one.
因为这个… 可能不太像催眠曲
- Oh, I should go. - It's too late for that now.
哦 我该走了 现在已经太晚了
I'm such a terrible faun.
我是这么坏的一个人羊
Oh, no.
哦 不
You're the nicest faun I've ever met.
你是我见过的最好的人羊
Then I'm afraid you've had a very poor sampling.
恐怕那是因为你没有见过 好的人羊
No. You can't have done anything that bad.
不 你不可能做过什么坏事
It's not something I have done, Lucy Pevensie.
不是我以前做过的事情 露西派文西
It's something l am doing.
而是我现在正在做的事情
What are you doing?
你在做什么 ?
I'm kidnapping you.
我正在扬骗你
It was the White Witch.
是白女下
She's the one who makes it always winter, always cold. She gave orders.
是她让这里总是寒冬 是她下的命令
If any of us ever find a human wandering in the woods,
如果我们在树林里发现人类
we're supposed to turn it over to her.
就得把他们抓起来交给她
But, Mr. Tumnus, you wouldn't.
可是 吐纳思先生 你不会这么做的
I thought you were my friend.
我还以为你是我的朋友
Now. She may already know you're here.
现在她可能已经知道 你在这几了
The woods are full of her spies.
树林里到处都是她的耳目
Even some of the trees are on her side.
甚至连一些树都站在她那边
Can you find your way back from here?
你认得从这里回去的路吗 ?
- [ think so. - All right.
应该认得 那好
Will you be all right?
你不会有事吧 ?
Hey, hey, hey.
np里 .--
I'm sorry. I'm so sorry.
对不起 真的很对不起
Here.
还给你
Keep it. You need it more than I do.
你留着吧 你比我更需要它
No matter what happens, Lucy Pevensie, lam glad to have met you.
不管发生什么事 露西派文西 我都很高兴认识你
You've made me feel warmer than I've felt in a hundred years.
过去一百年来 我都没有党得这么温暖过
Now go.
走吧
Go!
快走
..99, 100.
…99 100
Ready or not, here I come!
不管准备好了没有 我来啦
It's all right! I'm back! I'm all right!
好啦 我回来了 我没事
Shut up! He's coming!
闭跑 他过来了
You know, I'm not sure you two have quite got the idea of this game.
你们两个好像不太清楚 这个游戏的规则
Weren't you wondering where I was?
你不想知道我去了哪儿吗?
That's the point. That was why he was seeking you.
估键就在这几 所以他才会来找你
Does this mean I win?
这是不是表示我赢了?
I don't think Lucy wants to play anymore.
我想露西不想再玩了
I've been gone for hours.
我离开了好几个钟头了
Lucy, the only wood in here is the back of the wardrobe.
这里唯一的木头就是衣橱板
One game at a time, Lu. We don't all have your imagination.
一雪只玩一个游戏 露 我们没有你那么丰富的想象力
But I wasn't imagining!
那不是我想象出来的
That's enough, Lucy.
够了 露西
wouldn't lie about this!
我不会撒这种谎
Well, I believe you.
我相信你
- You do? - Yeah, of course.
真的吗 ? 当然
Didn't I tell you about the field in the cupboards?
我没跟你说过 浴室柜子里有个足球场吗 ?
Will you just stop?
闭中好吗 ?
You just have to make everything worse, don't you?
你非要把事情青得更糟是吗 ?
- It was just a joke! - When are you gonna learn to grow up?
我只是开个玩笑 你什么时候才能长大?
Shut up! You think you're Dad, but you're not!
闭哎 你以为你是和爸区 可你不是
Well, that was nicely handled.
然理得真漂亮
But... it really was there.
可是…它真的在那儿
Susan's right, Lucy.
苏珊说得对 露西
That's enough.
够了
Lucy.
露西
Where are you?
你在哪儿 ?
Hope you're not afraid of the dark.
希望你不要怕黑
Lucy?
露西?
Lucy!
露西
Where are you?
你在哪儿 ?
I think I believe you now.
现在我相信你的话了
Lucy.
露西
Lucy?
露西?
- Leave me alone! - What is it now, Ginarrbrik?
放开我 又怎么了 长胡子?
Make him let me go! I didn't do anything wrong!
让他放开我 我没做错事
How dare you address the Queen of Narnia?
你竞敢这样对纳尼亚女王说话
I didn't know!
我又不知道
- You will know her better hereafter! - Wait!
以后你就会知道很清楚了 等等
What is your name, Son of Adam?
你叫什么名字 亚当的儿子?
Edmund.
爱德蒙
And how, Edmund, did you come to enter my dominion?
你怎么会进入我的王国 ?
I'm not sure. I was just following my sister.
我也不清楚 我是跟着我妹妹进来的
- Your sister? How many are you? - Four.
你妹妹?你们兄弟姐妹共几个 四个
Lucy's the only one that's been here before.
只有露西来过这里
She said she met some faun called Tumnus.
她说她碰到了一个 名叫旺纳思的人羊
Peter and Susan didn't believe her. I didn't either.
彼得和苏珊不相信她 我也不相信
Edmund, you look so cold. Will you come and sit with me?
爱德蒙 你看上去冻坏了 上来跟我坐在一起吧
Now, how about something hot to drink?
要不要喝点热的东西 ?
Yes, please, Your Majesty.
好的 女王陛下
Your drink, sire.
你的饮料 先生
How did you do that?
你是怎么做到的?
l can make anything you like.
我能变出你想要的任何东西
Can you make me taller?
你能让我变高一点吗?
Anything you'd like to eat.
任何你想吃的东西
Turkish delight?
土耳其软糖 ?
Edmund?
爱德蒙?
I would very much like to meet the rest of your family.
我很想见见你的家人
Why?
为什么 ?
They're nothing special.
他们没什么特别的地方
Oh, I'm sure they're not nearly as delightful as you are.
哦 他们背定没有你 这么讨人喜欢
But you see, Edmund, l have no children of my own.
可是 爱德蒙 我没有自己的孩子
And you are exactly the sort of boy
日后我可以让你…
who I could see, one day, becoming Prince of Narnia.
…成为纳尼亚的王子
Maybe even King.
站至是国王
Really?
真的吗 ?
Of course, you'd have to bring your family.
当然了 你得把你的家人带来
Do you mean, Peter would be king too?
你是说彼得也会成为国王?
No! No, no.
不…-
But a king needs servants.
可是国王需要什人
I guess I could bring 'em.
我想我能把他们带来
Beyond these woods, you see those two hills?
在那些树林后面 你看到那两座山了吗 ?
My house is right between them.
我的宫殿就在那两座山之间
You'd love it there, Edmund.
你会喜欢那儿的 爱德蒙
It has whole rooms simply stuffed with Turkish delight.
那里有满屋子的土耳其软糖
- Couldn't l have some more now? - No!
我现在能再吃一点吗? 不行
Don't want to ruin your appetite.
我不想破坏你的胃口
Besides, you and I are going to be seeing each other again very soon.
何况我们很快就会再炎见面的
l hope so, Your Majesty.
希望如此 女王了轩下
Until then, dear one. I'm gonna miss you.
在那之前 亲爱的 我会想你的
Edmund?
爱德蒙?
Oh, Edmund! You got in too!
哦 爱德蒙 你也来了
Isn't it wonderful?
是不是很奇妙 ?
- Where have you been? - With Mr. Tumnus. He's fine.
你去哪儿了? 去找吐纳思先生了 他没事
The White Witch hasn't found out anything about him meeting me.
白女焉不知道他见过我
The White Witch?
白女牌 ?
She calls herself the Queen of Narnia, but she really isn't.
她说自己是纳尼亚女王 但其实不是
Are you all right? You look awful.
你还好吧 ? 你的脸色很难看
Well, what'd you expect? I mean, it's freezing.
不然你还想怎样? 这里这么冷
- How do we get out of here? - Come on.
我们怎么出去呢 ? 跟我来
This way.
这按
Peter, Peter, wake up! Peter, wake up!
彼得 醒醒 彼得 醒醒
It's there! It's really there!
它在那儿 真的在那儿
- Lucy, what are you talking about? - Narnia!
露西 你在说什么 ? 纳尼亚
It's all in the wardrobe like I told you!
就在衣橱里 就像我跟你说过的那样
- You've just been dreaming, Lucy. - But l haven't!
你是在做梦 露西 我没有
l saw Mr. Tumnus again! And this time Edmund went too.
我又见到吐纳思先生了 这灵爱德蒙也去了
You... You saw the faun?
你…你看到那个人羊了?
Well, he didn't actually go there with me.
其实他并没有跟我一起 去吐纳思先生家
He...
他…-
What were you doing, Edmund?
你当时在干什么呢 爱德蒙?
I was just playing along.
我只是在联她演戏
I'm sorry, Peter.
对不起 彼得
I shouldn't have encouraged her,
我不应该鼓励她的
but you know what little children are like these days.
可你知道 现在的孩子 都是这样的
They just don't know when to stop pretending.
他们只是不知道 什么时候该停止假装
You children are one shenanigan shy of sleepin’ in the stable!
你们这些淘气的孩子 应该让你们住在马顾里才对
Professor. I'm sorry. I told them you were not to be disturbed.
教授 对不起 我告诉过他们不要打扰你
It's all right, Mrs. Macready. I'm sure there's an explanation.
没人关系 麦瑞莆太太 我相信这其中必有原因
But first of all, l think this one is in need of a little hot chocolate.
不过 首先我认为这个小姑娘 需要喝些热巧克力
Come along, dear.
来吧 亲爱的
You seem to have upset the delicate internal balance of my housekeeper.
你们好像把我的管家 搞得神经训弱
We're very sorry, sir. It won't happen again.
我们真的很抱散 先生 以后不会再发生这种事
It's our sister, sir. Lucy.
是因为我们的妹妹 露西
- The weeping girl. - Yes, sir.
那个哭泣的小姑娘 对 先生
- She's upset. - Hence the weeping.
她很难过 所以才会哭泣
It's nothing.
没事的
- We can handle it. - Oh, I can see that.
我们能铸理好 这我能看得出来
She thinks she's found a magical land.
她自以为发现了一个魔法王国
In the upstairs wardrobe.
就在楼上的衣橱里
What did you say?
你说什么 ?
The wardrobe, upstairs.
楼上的胡柏
Lucy thinks she's found a forest inside.
露西以为她在里面 找到了一片森林
She won't stop going on about it.
她一直在说这件事
- What was it like? - Like talking to a lunatic.
那是什么样的? 就像在跟一个疯子对话
No, no, no, not her. The forest.
我不是指她 我是说那片森林
- You're not saying you believe her? - You don't?
你不会是说你相信她吧 ? 你们不相信她 ?
But of course not.
当然不相信
I mean, logically, it's impossible.
我是说 从逻辑上说来 这是不可能的
What do they teach in schools these days?
现在的学校都在教些什么啊?
Edmund said they were only pretending.
爱德蒙说他们是在玩假装游戏
He's usually the more truthful one, is he?
他比较诚实可靠 是吗?
No. This would be the first time.
不 这可能是第一灵
Well, if she's not mad and she's not lying,
如果她既没疯也没撒谎
then logically we must assume she's telling the truth.
那么从逻辑上说来 我们就得假定她说的是实话
You're saying that we should just believe her?
你是说我们应该相信她 ?
She's your sister, isn't she? You're her family.
她是你们的妹妹 不是吗? 你们是她的家人
You might just try acting like one.
你们应该表现得像一家人
Peter winds up, poised to take yet another wicket!
彼得挥动手展 准备再投一球
Wake up, Dolly Daydream.
醒醒吧 别做和白日禁了
Why can't we play hide and seek again?
我们干硫不再玩捉迷藏呢?
I thought you said it was a kid's game.
我记得你说那是孩子玩的游戏
Besides, we could all use the fresh air.
再说了 我们可以呼吸一下新鲜空气
It's not like there isn't air inside.
屋里又不是没有空气
- Are you ready? - Are you?
准备好了吗 ? 你呢 ?
- Well done, Ed. - You bowled it!
二得好 爱德 是你扔的球
- What on earth is goin' on? - The Macready!
这到底是怎么回事? 是麦瑞莆太太
Come on!
快跑
No, no, back, back, back!
不…回去…-
- Come on! - You've got to be joking.
快来啊 你是在开玩笑吧
Get back!
往后一点
- My toe! - I'm not on your toe!
我的脚开头 我又没踩你的聊对头
- Move back. - Will you stop shoving?
往后一点 别推我好吗 ?
Impossible.
不可能
Don't worry.
别担心
I'm sure it's just your imagination.
我至青定这只是你们的想象
I don't suppose saying we're sorry
我想 光说一声对不起
- would quite cover it. - No. It wouldn't.
…可能没什么用 对 是没用
But that might!
但那个可能有用
Stop it!
别冰了
You little liar.
你这个小骗子
- You didn't believe her, either. - Apologize to Lucy.
你也不相信她啊 向露西道娄
- Say you're sorry. - All right! I'm sorry.
说对不起 好啦 对不起
That's all right.
没父系
Some children just don't know when to stop pretending.
有些孩子只是不知道 什么时候该停止假装
Maybe we should go back.
也许我们该回去了
But shouldn't we at least take a look around?
我们至少应该四处逛才吧 ?
I think Lucy should decide.
我想这应该由串西来决定
I'd like you all to meet Mr. Tumnus!
我想带你们去看看吐纳思先生
Well, then Mr. Tumnus it is.
好 那就去看吐纳思先生
But we can't go hiking in the snow dressed like this.
可是我们不能穿得这么少 走在才地里
No.
对
But I'm sure the professor wouldn't mind us using these.
但我想教授不会介意 我们借穿一下这个
Anyway, if you think about it logically,
不管怎样 从逻辑上来说
we're not even taking them out of the wardrobe.
我们甚至没有 把这些衣服拿出衣橱
- But that's a girl's coat! - l know.
可那是女孩子穿的 我知道
..lots and lots of lovely food, and we'll have lots and lots of...
…有很多很多好吃的东西 我们还会有很多很多…
Lu?
露?
Lucy!
露西
Who would do something like this?
谁会做出这种事 ?
"The Faun Tumnus is hereby charged
「 人羊吐纳思
with High Treason against Her Imperial Majesty,
因背叛纳尼亚女王导迪丝陆下
Jadis, Queen of Narnia,
诲扩女王陆下的数人
for comforting her enemies and fraternizing with humans.
与人类交好 而被判处叛国界
Signed Maugrim, Captain of the Secret Police.
秘密警察队长毛格林签字
Long Live the Queen."
女王陆下万岁]
All right. Now we really should go back.
现在我们真的该回去了
But what about Mr. Tumnus?
可呈纳思先生怎么办?
If he was arrested just for being with a human,
如果他仅仅因为跟人类交往
- [don't think there's much we can do. - You don't understand, do you?
那我想我们帮不上什么忙 你们并不明白 是吧?
I'm the human.
我就是那个人类
She must have found out he helped me.
她肯定是发现了他帮过我
- Maybe we could call the police. - These are the police.
也许我们可以报警 抓他的就是警察
Don't worry, Lu. We'll think of something.
别担心 露 我们会想出办法的
Why?
为什么 ?
I mean, he's a criminal.
我是说 他是个罪犯
Did that bird just "psst" us?
那只鸟儿是不是在招呼我们 ?
It... It's a beaver.
是一只海狸
Here, boy.
过来 小东西
l ain't gonna smell it, if that's what you want.
如果你是想让我闻闻你的手 我可做不到
Sorry.
对不起
Lucy Pevensie?
露西派文西 ?
Yes?
我是
That's the hankie I gave to Mr. Tum...
那是我的手绢 我送给呈…
Tumnus. He got it to me just before they took him.
吐纳思 他在被抓之前 把手绢交给了我
Is he all right?
他还好吗 ?
Further in.
到里面再说
- What are you doing? - She's right.
你在干什么 ? 她是对的
How do we know we can trust him?
你怎么知道我们能相信他 ?
He said he knows the faun.
他说他认识人羊
He's a beaver. He shouldn't be saying anything!
他是个海狸 他不应该会说话
Everything all right?
一切都还好吧 ?
Yes. We were just talking.
没事 我们只是说说话
That's better left for safer quarters.
最好等到了安全的地方再说
He means the trees.
他指的是那些树
Come on. We don't want to be caught out here after nightfall.
快点 天黑之后可别采在这里
Blimey! Looks like the old girl has got the kettle on.
啊呀 看来老疲也 已经者上水了
Nice cup o' Rosy Lee.
来杯好喝的热荣
- It's lovely. - It's merely a trifle.
真可爱 只是个小玩意儿
Still plenty to do. Ain't quite finished it yet.
还没有全部完工呢
It'll look the business when it is, though.
等完工了就会像那么回事了
Beaver, is that you? I've been worried sick!
海狸 是你吗 ?我快担心死了
If l find you've been out with Badger again, I...
要是被我发现你又去找多 我就…
Well, those aren't badgers.
看来不是区
Oh, I never thought I'd live to see this day.
哦 我做梦也没想到 我会活着见到这一天
Look at my fur. You couldn't give me ten minutes warning?
看看我的毛有多乱 你就不能 提前个十分钟通知我吗 ?
I'd have given a week if l thought it would've helped.
如果有用的话 我给你一个礼拜都行
Oh, come inside, and we'll see if we can't get you some food,
进来吧 证我们看看 能不能给你们青点吃的
and some civilized company.
外加一些有教养的陪伴
Now, careful. Watch your step.
慢点 小心脚下
Excuse the mess.
抱散 屋子里很乱
Can't get Mr. Beaver to get out of his chair.
海狸先生成天坐在那几 从不收捡家务
Enjoyin' the scenery, are we?
你是在欣赏风景吗 ?
Isn't there anything we can do to help Tumnus?
我们怎么才能帮上吐纳思?
They'll have taken him to the Witch's. You know what they say.
他们会把他带到女焉那里 你们也知道
There's few that go through them gates that come out again.
只要进入那道大门 很少有人还能再出来
Fish 'n' chips?
鱼和苗条 ?
But there is hope, dear. Lots of hope.
不过还是有希望的 很大的希望
Oh, yeah, there's a right bit more than hope!
对 不只是希望而已
Aslan is on the move.
亚斯蓝正在行动
Who's Aslan?
亚斯蓝是谁 ?
You cheeky little blighter.
你可真爱开玩笑
What?
干骂 ?
- You don't know, do you? - We haven't exactly been here long.
你们真的不知道 ? 我们刚到这几没多妈
Well, he's only the king of the whole wood.
他是整个森林唯一的君王
The top geezer. The real King of Narnia.
是最高领袖 是纳尼亚真正的国王
- He's been away for a long while. - But he's just got back!
他离开了很长时间 但他已经回来了
And he's waitin’ for you near the Stone Table!
他正在石桌那边等着你们
- He's waiting for us? - You're bloomin' joking!
他在等着我们 ? 你肯定是在说笑
They don't even know about the prophecy!
他们甚至连那个预言都不知道
- Well, then... - Look.
那么… 听着
Aslan's return,
亚斯蓝的为来
Tumnus' arrest, the secret police,
吐纳思的被捕 秘密敖察
it's all happening because of you!
这一切都是因为你们
- You're blaming us? - No! Not blaming.
你是在责怪我们 ? 不 不是责怪
- Thanking you. - There's a prophecy.
是感谢你们 我们这儿有一个预言
"When Adam's flesh and Adam's bone
「 一旦亚当的埃肉
sits at Cair Paravel in throne,
…登上凯尔帕拉瓦的王位
the evil time will be over and done."
罪恶的年代就将一去不返1
- That doesn't really rhyme. - [know it don't.
这个预言并不押韵 这我知道
You're kinda missin’ the point!
重点不在这几
It has long been foretold
有一个吉老的预言说
that two Sons of Adam and two Daughters of Eve
亚当的两个儿子 和夏娃的两个女儿
will defeat the White Witch and restore peace to Narnia.
…将会打败和白女焉 让纳尼亚重获和平
And you think we're the ones?
你认为那就是我们 ?
You'd better be, 'cause Aslan's already fitted out your army.
最好如此 因为亚斯蓝已经 为你们准备好了你们的军队
- Our army? - Mum sent us away
我们的军队 ? 妈妈把我们送走
so we wouldn't get caught up in a war.
…就是为了不让我们着入战争
I think you've made a mistake.
我想你们开错了
- We're not heroes. - We're from Finchley.
我们不是什么英雄 我们来自芬奇里
Thank you for your hospitality.
谢谢你们的款待
- But we really have to go. - No, you can't just leave!
可我们真的得走了 不 你们不能就这么一走了之
He's right. We have to help Mr. Tumnus.
他说的对 我们得救吐纳思先生
It's out of our hands.
我们无能为力
I'm sorry,
对不起
but it's time the four of us were getting home. Ed?
可我们四个得回家了 爱德?
Ed?
爱德 ?
- I'm gonna kill him. - You may not have to.
我要杀了他 也许用不着你动手
Has Edmund ever been to Narnia before?
爱德蒙以前来过纳尼亚吗 ?
Hurry!
快点
- Edmund! - They'll hear you!
爱德蒙 他们会听到的
No!
不
- Get off! - You're playing into her hands.
放开我 你们这么做等于自投罗网
- We can't just let him go! - He's our brother!
我们不能就这样让他走了 他是我们的兄弟
He's the bait! The Witch wants all four of you!
他是个诱包 女巫想把你们四个全都抓住
- Why? - To stop the prophecy from coming true.
为什么 ? 为了阻止预言成为现实
To kill you!
为了杀死你们
- This is all your fault. - My fault?
都是你的错 我的错?
None of this would have happened if you had listened to me!
要是你听我的话 就不会发生这些事了
- You knew this would happen. - [didn't know.
你早就知道会发生这些事 ? 我不知道
Which is why we should have left while we could!
所以我们才应该趁早离开
Stop it!
别吵了
- This isn't going to help Edmund. - She's right.
这样救不了爱德蒙 她说的对
Only Aslan can help your brother now.
现在只有亚斯蓝 能救你们的兄弟
Then take us to him.
那就带我们去找他
Be still, stranger, or you'll never move again.
别动 陌生人 不然你就死定了
- Who are you? - I'm Edmund!
你是谁? 我叫爱德蒙
I met the Queen in the woods! She told me to come back here!
我在森林里遇见了女王 她叫我到这里来找她
I'm a Son of Adam!
我是亚当的儿子
My apologies, fortunate favorite of the queen.
抱散 女王的幸运几
Or else, not so fortunate.
不然你就没这么幸运了
Right this way.
这边走
Wait here.
在这儿等着
Like it?
喜欢吗 ?
Yes, Your Majesty.
喜欢 女王陛下
I thought you might.
我就知道你会喜欢
Tell me, Edmund...
告诉我 爱德蒙
Are your sisters deaf?
你的姐妹们是俐子吗 ?
No.
不是
And your brother, is he...
你的哥哥 他…
. unintelligent?
…-很策吗
Well, I think so. But Mum says...
我觉得是这样 可妈妈说…
Then how dare you come alone?!
那你怎么敢一个人前来 ?
- [ tried! - Edmund, I asked so little of you.
我试过了 爱德蒙 我对你就这么一点要求
- They just don't listen to me! - You couldn't even do that.
他们不背听我的 你连这点小事都办不到
I did bring them halfway.
我已经把他们带到了半路
They're at the little house at the dam with the Beavers.
他们就在水坝边的小房子里 跟海狸夫妇果在一起
Well.
这么说
l suppose you're not a total loss then, are you?
看来你并非一事无成 是吧 ?
could I maybe have some more Turkish delight now?
我现在能不能吃点土耳其软糖
Our guest is hungry.
我们的客人钱了
This way for your num-nums.
跟着我去吃美食吧
Maugrim?
毛格林 ?
You know what to do.
你知道该怎么做吧
Hurry, Mother! They're after us!
快点 孩子他妈 他们追来了
- Oh, right then. - What's she doing?
马上就好 她在干什么 ?
Oh, you'll be thanking me later.
哦 等会儿你们会感谢我的
It's a long journey and Beaver gets pretty cranky when he's hungry.
路途很长 而我们家海狸 只要一饿就会抓狂
I'm cranky now!
我现在就很抓狂
Take them.
抓住它们
- Do you think we'll need jam? - Only if the Witch serves toast.
你认为我们会需要果着吗 ? 如果女巫提供面包的话
Hurry.
快点
Badger and me dug this. Comes out right near his place.
这是我跟多一起控的 出己就在他家附近
You told me it led to your mum's!
你跟我说这是通到你妈妈家的
Lucy!
露西
They're in the tunnel.
他们进隧道了
- Quick! This way. - Hurry!
快点 这色 快点
- Run! - Quick! Quick! Quick!
快跑 快点…-
You should have brought a map!
你应该带张地图的
There wasn't room next to the jam.
你塞满了果普 哪放得下地图
Come on, Lucy!
快点 露西
What happened here?
这是怎么回事?
This is what becomes of those who cross the Witch.
这就是跟女焉作对的下场
You take one more step, traitor, and I'll chew you to splinters!
叛徒 你再往前一步 我就把你咬成碎片
Relax. I'm one of the good guys.
放松 我是好人
Yeah? Well, you look an awful lot like one of the bad ones.
是吗?你看上去更像坏人
An unfortunate family resemblance.
很不幸的家族遗传
But we can argue breeding later. Right now we've got to move.
以后再讨论血统的问题 现在我们得赶快行动
What did you have in mind?
你有什么计划 ?
Greetings, gents.
你们好啊 各位
- Lost something, have we? - Don't patronize me!
丢了东西是吗 ? 少来这和套
I know where your allegiance lies.
我知道你们狐狸的本性
We're looking for some humans.
我们在寻找一些人类
Humans? Here in Narnia?
人类?在纳尼亚?
That's a valuable bit of information, don't you think?
那是非常有价值的情报 你不觉得吗 ?
Your reward is your life.
酬劳就是饶你一命
It's not much,
虽然不多
but still.
但是足够了
Where are the fugitives?
那些逃犯去哪儿了?
North. They ran north.
北边 他们向北边跑去了
Smell them out.
闻闻他们在哪儿
They were helping Tumnus. The Witch got here before I did.
他们玫助了吐纳思 女焉比我先赶到这几
Are you all right?
你还好吧 ?
Well, l wish I could say their bark was worse than their bite.
真希望我可以说 他们只会叫唤不会咬人
Stop squirming! You're worse than Beaver on bath day.
别扭来振去了 你比洗澡时的海狸还错糙
Worst day of the year.
一年中最糟的一天
Thank you for your kindness,
谢谢你的好意
but that's all the cure I have time for.
不过我没时间疗伤了
You're leaving?
你要走了 ?
It has been a pleasure, My Queen, and an honor, but time is short
女王轩下 这是我的荣桩 和荣光 可时间很有限
and Aslan himself has asked me to gather more troops.
亚斯蓝请我聚集更多的军队
- You've seen Aslan? - What's he like?
你见过亚斯蓝 ? 他是什么样子的 ?
Like everything we've ever heard.
跟传说中的一模一样
You'll be glad to have him by your side in the battle against the Witch.
你会很高兴 有他与你并局对抗女正
But we're not planning on fighting any witch.
可我们没打算对抗什么女巫
But surely, King Peter, the prophecy!
可这是必然的 彼得国王 那个预言
We can't go to war without you.
没有你 我们无法战斗
We just want our brother back.
我们只想找回我们的兄弟
If...
如果…
If you're not going to eat that...
如果你不吃那个的话…
I'd get up, but...
我很想站起来 可是…
..but my legs.
可是我的腿…
Mr. Tumnus.
你是吐纳思先生
What's left of him.
是他残留的部分
- You're Lucy Pevensie's brother. - I'm Edmund.
你是露西派文西的哥哥 我叫爱德蒙
Yes. Yes, you have the same nose.
对 你们的鼻子很像
Is your sister all right?
你妹妹还好吧 ?
Is she safe?
她安全吗 ?
I don't know.
我不知道
My police tore that dam apart.
我的警察将水坝全都拆了
Your little family are nowhere to be found.
也没有找到你的家人
- Where did they go? - [don't know!
他们去哪儿了? 我不知道
Then you're of no further use to me.
那你对我就没有任何用处了
Wait! The beaver said something about Aslan!
等等 海狸提到了亚斯蓝什么的
Aslan?
亚斯蓝 ?
Where?
在哪儿 ?
el. - He's a stranger here, Your Majesty.
他对这几很陌生 女王隆下
He can't be expected to know anything.
他什么都不知道
I said... where is Aslan?
我说了…亚斯蓝在哪儿 ?
I... [don't know.
我…我不知道
I left before they said anything.
我走的时候他们还没说呢
l wanted to see you!
当时我只想来见你
Guard!
卫兵
Your Majesty.
陛下
Release the faun.
放了人羊
Do you know why you're here, faun?
人羊 你知道 你为什么会被抓到这儿吗 ?
Because I believe in a free Narnia.
因为我相信纳尼亚应该自由
You're here...
你被抓到这儿…
..because he turned you in.
…是因为他告发了你
For sweeties.
就为了一些糖果
Take him upstairs.
把他带上楼
And ready my sleigh.
备好我的雪要
Edmund misses his family.
爱德蒙想念他的家人了
Now, Aslan's camp is near the Stone Table
亚斯蓝的营地在石旧附近
- just across the frozen river. - River?
穿过结冰的河就到了 河?
The river's been frozen solid for a hundred years.
河水已经冻结了一百年
- It's so far. - It's the world, dear.
好远啊 这是整个世界 亲爱的
Did you expect it to be small?
难道你指望它会很小吗 ?
Smaller.
小一点
When you're ready, Son of Adam.
就等你了 亚当的儿子
Come on, humans! While we're still young.
快点 人类 趁着我们还年轻
If he tells us to hurry one more time,
他要是再催促我们
I'm gonna turn him into a big, fluffy hat.
一顶毛绕绒的幅子
Hurry up! Come on!
快点 快
- He is getting a little bossy. - No! Behind you! It's her!
他开始有点专横了 不 在你们后面 是她
- Run! Run! - Run!
快跑… 快跑
Hurry!
快点
Inside!
进去
Dive! Dive!
跳下去…
Quick! Quick, quick, quick!
快点…-
Maybe she's gone.
也许她已经走了
- Lsuppose I'll go look. - No!
我出去看看 不
You're worth nothing to Narnia dead.
你死了纳尼亚就完了
Well, neither are you, Beaver.
你也一样 海狸
Thanks, sweetheart.
谢谢你 亲爱的
What's that? What's...?
那是什么 那是… ?
Come out! Come out!
出来吧…
l hope you've all been good ‘cause there's someone here to see you!
希望你们一直都很乖 因为有人来看你们了
Merry Christmas, sir.
圣诞快乐 圣诞老人
It certainly is, Lucy, since you have arrived.
我很快乐 露西 因为你们来了
Look, I've put up with a lot since I got here, but this...
来这儿之后我就一直在忍耐 可是这个…
- We thought you were the Witch. - Yes, yes, I'm sorry about that,
我们还以为你是女焉 对此我很抱攻
but in my defense, I have been driving one of these longer than the Witch.
不过我要兰解一名 我驾雪机的时间比女焉要久
I thought there was no Christmas in Narnia.
我记得纳尼亚没有圣诞节
No. Not for a long time.
对 很久都没有了
But the hope that you have brought, Your Majesties,
可是 各位陛下 你们所带来的希望
is finally starting to weaken the Witch's power.
…已经开始亨弱女焉的力量
Still, l dare say you could do with these.
不过我敢说 你们会用得上这些
Presents!
圣诞礼物
The juice of the fire-flower.
火焰花的汁液
One drop will cure any injury.
一滴就能治疗任何伤口
And though I hope you never have to use it...
虽然我希望你永远也用不上它
Thank you, sir,
谢谢你 圣诞老人
but I think I could be brave enough.
但我想我会足够勇敢的
I'm sure you could.
我敢肯定你会的
But battles are ugly affairs.
可战争是于天的
Susan.
苏表
Trust in this bow and it will not easily miss.
相信这把号 它就会百发百中
What happened to "battles are ugly affairs"?
你不是说 「 战争是隆陋的上 吗?
Though you don't seem to have a problem making yourself heard,
虽说你的嗓门不小
blow on this and wherever you are,
但只要吹响这个 不管你在哪里
help will come.
都会得到帮助
Thanks.
谢谢
Peter.
彼得
The time to use these may be near at hand.
你可能很快就会用上这些东西
Thank you, sir.
谢谢你 圣诞老人
These are tools, not toys.
这些是工具 而不是玩具
Bear them well and wisely.
好好地使用它们
Now, I must be off.
现在我得走了
Winter is almost over,
冬天就快结束了
and things do pile up when you've been gone a hundred years.
一百年不在 事情都快难成山了
Long live Aslan!
亚斯蓝万岁
And Merry Christmas!
圣诞快乐
- See you next year! - Goodbye!
明年见 再见
Told you he was real.
我早说过他是真的嘛
He said winter was almost over.
他说冬天就快结束了
You know what that means.
明白那是什么意思吗 ?
No more ice.
不再有冰了
- We need to cross, now! - Don't beavers make dams?
我们得马上过河 海狸不是会修水坝吗 ?
- I'm not that fast, dear. - Come on!
我的动作没那么快 亲爱的 快点
Wait! Will you think about this for a minute?
等等 你要不要 先花点时间考谍一下?
- We don't have a minute. - I'm just trying to be realistic.
我们没有时间了 我只是想现实一点
No, you're trying to be smart. As usual.
不 你只是想卖弄聪明 就像往常那样
Wait. Maybe I should go first.
等等 也许该让我先过去
Maybe you should.
也许是该这样
You've been sneaking second helpings, haven't you?
你又偷吃了东西 是不是?
Well, you never know which meal's gonna be your last.
谁也不知道 哪顿饭会是最后一顿
Especially with your cooking.
特别是吃你做的菜
If Mum knew what we were doing...
如果妈妈知道我们在做什么…
Mum's not here.
妈妈不在这几
Oh, no!
哦 不
Run!
快跑
Hurry!
快点
- No! - Peter!
不 彼得
Put that down, boy.
放下剑 孩子
- Someone could get hurt. - Don't worry about me!
你会伤到人的 别为我担心
Run him through!
干掉他
Leave now while you can, and your brother leaves with you.
如果你们现在离开 我们就放了你弟弟
Stop, Peter! Maybe we should listen to him!
住手 彼得 也许我们该听他的
Smart girl.
聪明的女孩
Don't listen to him! Kill him! Kill him now!
别听他的 杀了他 快杀了他
Oh, come on. This isn't your war.
拜托 这场战争与你们无估
All my Queen wants is for you to take your family and go.
我们的女王只希望 你带上家人离开这里
Look, just because some man in a red coat hands you a sword,
听着 一个穿着红外套的人 送你一把剑
it doesn't make you a hero! Just drop it!
并不代表你就变成英雄了 放下剑
No, Peter! Narnia needs you!
不 彼得 纳尼亚需要你
Gut him while you still have a chance!
趁你还有机会快杀了他
What's it gonna be, Son of Adam? I won't wait forever.
你怎么想 亚当的儿子? 我不会一直等在这几
And neither will the river.
这条河也不会
Peter!
彼得
Lovely.
真舒服
What have you done?
你干了什么?
Lucy!
露西
Has anyone seen my coat?
有人见到我的外套了吗 ?
Don't you worry, dear.
别担心 亲爱的
Your brother's got you well looked after.
你哥哥把你辕顾得很好
And I don't think you'll be needing those coats anymore.
而且我不认为 你们还需要那些外套
It's so warm out.
外面变得这么暖和了
I'll go and check the sleigh.
我去检查一下雪权
Your Majesty.
陛下
We found the traitor. He was rallying your enemies near the Shuddering Woods.
我们找到叛徒了 他正在树木里纠集您的数人
Nice of you to drop in.
欢迎你的到访
You were so helpful to my wolves last night.
昨晚你真是 帮了我的狼群一个大忙
Perhaps you can help me now.
也许现在你能帮帮我的忙
- Forgive me, Your Majesty. - Oh, don't waste time with flattery.
请原谅 陛下 别再甜言蜜语地浪费时间了
Not to seem rude, but I wasn't actually talking to you.
我不想这么粗鲁 不过我并不是在下你说话
Where are the humans headed?
那些人类往哪儿去了?
Wait! No! Don't. The beaver said something about the Stone Table,
等等 不要 海狸提到过石旧什么的
and that Aslan had an army there.
还说亚斯蓝在那里有军队
An army?
军队 ?
Thank you, Edmund.
谢谢你 爱德蒙
I'm glad this creature got to see some honesty...
我很高兴这个畜牧 见识到了什么叫做诚实
- ...before he dies. - No!
…在他临死之前 不要
Think about whose side you're on, Edmund.
想清楚你站在哪边 爱德蒙
..or theirs.
…还是他们那边
Go on ahead. Gather the faithful.
去吧 把那些 患诚可靠的手下聚集起来
If i's a war Aslan wants...
如果亚斯蓝想要战争…
.it's a war he shall get.
…那就给他战争
Why are they all staring at us?
他们为什么都时着我们 ?
Maybe they think you look funny.
也许是因为你看上去很可笑
Stop your fussing. You look lovely.
别弄了 你看上去漂亮极了
We have come to see Aslan.
我们是来见亚斯蓝的
Welcome, Peter, Son of Adam.
欢迎你 彼得 亚当的儿子
Welcome, Susan and Lucy, Daughters of Eve.
欢迎你们 苏玛和露西 夏娃的女儿
And welcome to you, Beavers. You have my thanks.
欢迎你们 海狸夫妇 我训心感谢你们
But where is the fourth?
可第四个孩子呢 ?
That's why we're here, sir.
我们正是为此而来 先生
We need your help.
我们需要你的帮助
We had a little trouble along the way.
我们在路上遇到了一点小麻烦
Our brother's been captured by the White Witch.
我们的兄弟被白女和焉抓走了
Captured? How could this happen?
抓走了? 这怎么可能 ?
He betrayed them, Your Majesty.
他藻叛了他们 陛下
- Then he has betrayed us all! - Peace, Oreius.
那他就等于背叛了我们所有人 安静 欧瑞斯
I'm sure there's an explanation.
我相信这其中必有原因
Il was too hard on him.
我对他太严厉了
We all were.
我们都是
Sir, he's our brother.
他是我们的兄弟
I know, dear one.
我知道 亲爱的
But that only makes the betrayal all the worse.
可这只让他的背叛行为更严重
This may be harder than you think.
这件事可能 比你们想象的更困难
That is Cair Paravel, the castle of the four thrones.
那就是凯尔帕拉瓦 那里有四个王位
In one of which you will sit, Peter, as High King.
彼得 你将坐上其中一个 成为大帝
You doubt the prophecy?
你怀疑那个预言 ?
No. That's just it.
不 是这样的
Aslan, I'm not what you all think l am.
亚斯蓝 我不是你想象的那样
Peter Pevensie, formerly of Finchley.
彼得派文西 来自芬奇里
Beaver also mentioned that you planned on turning him into a hat.
海狸还说 你打算把他变成一顶惕子
Peter, there is a Deep Magic,
彼得 有一种远吉的高深魔法
more powerful than any of us,
比我们中的任何人都厉害
that rules over all of Narnia.
它统治着整个纳尼亚
It defines right from wrong,
判别是非
and governs all our destinies.
掌握我们所有人的命运
Yours... and mine.
你的…还有我的
But I couldn't even protect my own family.
可我甚至保扩不了自己的家人
You've brought them safely this far.
你已经安全地 把他们带到了这么远的地方
Not all of them.
但并非所有人
Peter, I will do what I can to help your brother,
彼得 我会尽我所能 去救你的兄弟
but I need you to consider what I ask of you.
但我需要你考虑一下 我对你的请求
I, too, want my family safe.
我也希望我的家人安全
Is our little prince uncomfortable?
我们的小王子是不是不舒服 ?
Does he want his pillow fluffed?
要不要帮他拍拍桃头 ?
Special treatment for the special boy!
特殊的人享有特殊的待遇
Isn't that what you wanted?
这不就是你想要的吗?
You look like Mum.
你看上去好像妈妈
Mum hasn't had a dress like this since before the war.
自从战前 妈妈就没穿过这样的衣服了
We should bring her one back. A whole trunk full!
我们应该给她带一件回去 带上整整一箱子
If we ever get back.
如果我们能回去的话
I'm sorry I'm like that.
很抱火我这么扫兴
We used to have fun together, didn't we?
我们以前玩得很开心 对吧 ?
Yes. Before you got boring.
对 在你变得烦人之前
Oh, really?
哦 真的吗?
Please don't try to run.
不要试图逃跑
- We're tired. - And we prefer to kill you quickly.
我们很累 而且我们想尽快解决你们
Susan!
苏表
Get back!
滚开
Peter!
彼得
Come on.
拜托
We've already been through this before.
我们已经玩过一灾这种游戏
We both know you haven't got it in you.
我们俩都清楚你没那个胆量
Peter! Watch out!
彼得 小心
No! Stay your weapons. This is Peter's battle.
不 收起你的武器 这是彼得的战争
You may think you're a king,
你以为你是国王
but you're going to die...
可你将会…
- .. like a dog! - Look out!
…像狗一样死去 小心
Peter!
彼得
After him.
跟着他
He'll lead you to Edmund.
他会带你们找到爱德蒙
Peter.
彼得
Clean your sword.
把剑控干净
Rise, Sir Peter Wolfs-Bane,
起来吧 层狼手彼得毅士
Knight of Narnia.
纳尼亚的骑士
The minotaurs will take the left flanks.
人身牛头怪会从左侧进攻
We'll keep the giants in reserve and send dwarfs in first.
我们让巨人留守 先让侏儒冲锋
The prisoner!
因犯
You're not going to kill me?
你不打算杀了我 ?
Not yet.
现在还不打算
We have work to do.
我们还有正事要做
Edmund!
爱德蒙
What's done is done.
过去的都已经过去了
There is no need to speak to Edmund about what is past.
从前的事就不必再提了
Hello.
你们好
- Are you all right? - I'm a little tired.
你还好吧 ? 有一点点累
Get some sleep.
去睡一会儿吧
..try not to wander off.
…可别迷路了
Narnia's not going to run out of toast, Ed.
纳尼亚有吃不完的面包 爱德
I'm sure they'll pack something up for the journey back.
应该打包一点在回去的路上吃
We're going home?
我们要回家了 ?
You are.
是你们
I promised Mum I'd keep you three safe.
要保证你们三个的安全
But it doesn't mean I can't stay behind and help.
但这不代表我不能留下来帮忙
But they need us.
可他们需要我们
All four of us.
我们四个
Lucy, it's too dangerous.
露西 这太危险了
You almost drowned! Edmund was almost killed!
你差点淹死 爱德蒙差点没命
Which is why we have to stay.
所以我们才要留下来
I've seen what the White Witch can do. And I've helped her do it.
我见过女焉的能耐
And we can't leave these people behind to suffer for it.
我们不能丢下这些人 让他们去遭受痛苦
l suppose that's it then.
我想就这么定了
Where are you going?
你去哪儿 ?
To get in some practice.
练习一下箭术
Come on, Ed! Sword point up, like Oreius showed us.
来吧 爱德 把剑举高 就像欧瑞斯教我们的那样
- En garde! - Now block.
预备 现在防守
- Hey! - Peter! Edmund!
哩 彼得 爱德蒙
Whoa, horsie!
哇噢 马几
My name is Philip.
我的名字叫菲利普
Sorry.
对不起
The Witch has demanded a meeting with Aslan.
女焉要求与亚斯蓝会面
She's on her way here.
她正在路上
Jadis, the Queen of Narnia!
项迪丝 纳尼亚女王
- Go away, Witch! - Empress of the Lone Islands!
滚出去 女焉 条岛女皇
You don't belong here! Go away!
你不属于这里 滚出去
You have a traitor in your midst, Aslan.
你们之间有一个叛徒 亚斯蓝
His offense was not against you.
他苛叛的并不是你
Have you forgotten the laws upon which Narnia was built?
你总了纳尼亚得以建国的律法
Do not cite the Deep Magic to me, Witch.
别下我引述高深魔法 女巫
l was there when it was written.
魔法制定时我也在场
Then you'll remember well that every traitor belongs to me.
那你就应该清楚地记得 每个叛徒都属于我
His blood is my property.
他的鲜血归我所有
Try and take him then.
那你就来拿拿看吧
Do you really think that mere force will deny me my right...
你真的以为仅赁武力 就能剥夺我的权利…
little King?
…小国王?
Aslan knows that unless I have blood, as the law demands,
亚斯蓝很清楚 除非我依照律法得到他的鲜血
all of Narnia will be overturned
不然整个纳尼亚将会在…
and perish in fire and water.
…烈火与洪水之中覆灭
That boy will die
那孩子将会…
on the Stone Table...
…死在石划之上
..a8 is tradition.
这是传统
You dare not refuse me.
你不敢拒绝我的
Enough.
够了
I shall talk with you alone.
我要跟你单独谈谈
She has renounced her claim on the Son of Adam's blood.
她不再要求得到 亚当儿子的鲜血
How do I know your promise will be kept?
我怎么知道你会守信呢 ?
Susan!
苏表
Shouldn't you both be in bed?
你们俩应该策在床上才对
We couldn't sleep.
我们瞧不着
Please, Aslan.
求求你 亚斯蓝
Couldn't we come with you?
我们能跟你一起去吗 ?
I would be glad of the company for a while.
如果你们能诬我一小会儿 我会很高兴
Thank you.
谢谢你们
It is time.
时候到了
From here, I must go on alone.
从这里开始 我必须一个人过去
But Aslan...
可是 亚斯蓝…
You have to trust me. For this must be done.
你们得相信我 因为这是必须要做的
Thank you, Susan.
谢谢你 苏珊
Thank you, Lucy.
谢谢你 露西
And farewell.
再见了
Behold. The great lion.
看啊 伟大的狮子王
Do you want some milk?
要来点牛奶吗 ?
Why doesn't he fight back?
他为什么不到击?
Bind him!
把他捆起来
Tie him up! Get him!
绑起来 担住他
Wait!
等等
Let him first be shaved.
先把他的毛薪看
Bring him to me.
把他带上来
You know, Aslan,
知道吗 亚斯蓝
I'm a little disappointed in you.
我对你有一点失望
Did you honestly think by all this that you could save the human traitor?
你真的以为 这样就能郁救那个人类叛徒?
You are giving me your life
你把性命交给我
and saving no one.
…却救不了任何人
So much for love.
爱也不过如此
Tonight...
今晚…
..the Deep Magic will be appeased!
…高深魔法将会得以遵守
But tomorrow,
但明天
we will take Narnia
我们将会拿下纳尼亚
forever!
直到永远
In that knowledge,
你就带着这份遗碱
despair...
绝望…
..and die!
…而死吧
The Great Cat...
这只大猫…
.1S dead!
…已经死了
General.
将军
Prepare your troops for battle.
证你的军队为战斗做好准备
However short it may be.
不管这场战斗会有多短暂
It's too late.
太晚了
He's gone.
他已经死了
He must have known what he was doing.
他和背定知道自己在做什么
Get away! Get away, all of you!
走开 你们这些东西
No. Look.
不 你看
We have to tell the others.
我们得去告诉其他人
- We can't just leave him! - Lucy, there's no time.
我们不能把他丢在这几 露西 没有时间了
They need to know.
他们需要知道这个消息
The trees.
让那些树帮忙
Be still, my Princes.
别紧张 王子
I bring grave news from your sisters.
你的姐妹们证我 带来一个不幸的消息
She's right.
她说的对
He's gone.
他死了
Then you'll have to lead us.
那样的话你就得带领我们
Peter, there's an army out there and it's ready to follow you.
彼得 军队就在外面 等候你的号令
- lL can't. - Aslan believed you could.
我做不到 亚斯蓝相信你能做到
And so dol.
我也相信
The Witch's army is nearing, sire. What are your orders?
女巫的军队正在逼近 陡下 您有什么指示?
They come, Your Highness, in numbers and weapons far greater than our own.
他们人数众多 武器精良
Numbers do not win a battle.
光赁人多并不能赢得战争
No. But I bet they help.
对 但人多还是会有所帮助
l have no interest in prisoners.
我对售让没有兴趣
Kill them all.
把他们杀得片甲不留
Go on!
冲啊
Look to the sky!
注意天上
Are you with me?
你会跟我来吗 ?
To the death.
赤死追随
For Narnia and for Aslan!
为了纳尼亚 为了亚斯蓝
Go!
冲啊
Go! For Aslan!
冲啊 为了亚斯蓝
We should go.
我们该走了
Susan!
苏表
Where's Aslan?
亚斯蓝呢 ?
What have they done?
他们做了什么 ?
Aslan!
亚斯蓝
But we saw the knife. The Witch.
可我们看见了刀子 还有女巫
If the Witch knew the true meaning of sacrifice,
如果女巫知道牺牲的真正侈义
she might have interpreted the Deep Magic differently.
她可能就会对高深魔法 有着不同的理解
That when a willing victim who has committed no treachery
当一个本身没有 背叛行为的牺牲者
is killed in a traitor's stead,
…自愿代替叛徒牺牡生命时
the Stone Table will crack
石划就会乔裂
and even death itself will turn backwards.
牺牲者也会死而复生
We sent the news that you were dead.
我们传出消息说你死了
Peter and Edmund will have gone to war.
彼得和爱德蒙已经上战场了
We have to help them.
我们得去帮帮他们
We will, dear one, but not alone.
亲爱的 我们会去帮他们的 但不仅仅是我们几个
Climb on my back.
想到我的背上来
We have far to go and little time to get there.
我们要去很远的地方 时间又很有限
And you may want to cover your ears.
你们最好揪上耳采
Fire!
放生
Yes!
器 匹
Fall back! Draw them to the rocks!
退后 把他们引到岩石这按
That's the signal. Come on!
是信号 快点
Where are we going?
我们要去哪儿 ?
Hang on!
抓稳了
Fall back!
撒退
Go on, fall back!
快点 撤退
Stop!
别过去
Mr. Tumnus!
吐纳思先生
Come, we must hurry and search the castle.
快 我们得赶快搜遍整个城堡
Peter will need everyone we can find.
彼得将会需要 我们找到的每一个人
Edmund! There's too many!
爱德蒙 他们的人太多了
Get out of here!
快离开这几
Get the girls and get them home!
找到苏班和露西 带他们回家
You heard him! Let's go!
你听到了 快走吧
Peter said get out of here!
彼得叫你快离开这几
Peter's not king yet.
彼得还不是国王呢
Impossible!
不可能
It is finished.
都结束了
- Peter!
彼得
Where's Edmund?
爱德蒙呢 ?
Edmund!
爱德蒙
When are you gonna learn to do as you're told?
你什么时候才能学会冬乖听话
To the glistening Eastern Sea,
闪耀的东方海洋
I give you Queen Lucy, the Valiant.
我赐予你露西女王 英勇非凡
To the great Western Wood,
伟大的西方森林
King Edmund, the Just.
爱德蒙国王 公正无私
To the radiant Southern Sun,
各烂的南方太阳
Queen Susan, the Gentle.
苏班女王 温柔和善
And to the clear Northern Sky,
晴朗的北方天空
I give you King Peter,
我赐予你彼得国王
the Magnificent.
至尊棠高
Once a King or Queen of Narnia,
在纳尼亚 一朝为王
always a King or Queen.
终身为王
May your wisdom grace us
愿你们的智慧给我们带来荣兆
until the stars rain down from the heavens.
直到天上的繁星坚落
Long live King Peter!
彼得国王万风
Long live King Edmund!
爱德蒙国王万岁
Long live Queen Susan!
苏了女王万岁
Long live Queen Lucy!
露西女王万岁
Don't worry.
别担心
We'll see him again.
我们还会再见到他的
- When? - In time.
什么时候? 总有一天
One day he'll be here and the next he won't.
有时他会出现 有时又会离去
But you mustn't press him.
但你不能勉强他
After all, he's not a tame lion.
要知道 他不是驯化了的狮子
No.
对
But he is good.
可他是好狮子
You need it more than I do.
你比我更需要它
Are you all right, Philip?
你还好吧 菲利普?
I'm not as young as I once was.
我已经不像以前那么年轻了
Come on, Ed.
快点 爱德
- Catching my breath. - That's all we'll catch at this rate.
让我喘口气 照这个样子我们什么都抓不到
- What did he say, Susan? - "Wait in the castle.
他刚才怎么说的来着 苏珊 ? 「 在城堡里等着
I'll get the stag myself."
我自己去抓白谭1
What's this?
这是什么 ?
It seems familiar.
看上去很眼热
As if from a dream.
好像来自梦里
Or a dream of a dream.
或者是个梦中梦
Spare Oom.
空皇疆
- Lucy! - Not again.
露西 又来了
- Lu? - Come on!
露? 快来
These aren't branches.
这些不是树枝
- They're coats. - Susan, you're on my foot!
是大衣 苏珊 你踩着我的聊了
Peter, move off!
彼得 快走啊
- Stop shoving. - Stop it!
别推我 别乱动
I'm not on your toe!
我没踩你的聊对头
There you are.
你们在这几骂
What were you all doing in the wardrobe?
你们几个在衣橱里干什么 ?
You wouldn't believe us if we told you, sir.
就算我们说出来 你也不会相信的 先生
Try me.
试试看吧
I don't think you'll get back in that way.
我不认为你能从那儿回去
You see... I've already tried.
你知道 我早就试过了
Will we ever go back?
我们还会再回去吗 ?
Oh, I expect so.
哦 我希望如此
But it'll probably happen when you're not looking for it.
但是 如果你不去找它 也许它自会出现
All the same...
不管怎样…
..best to keep your eyes open.
…了最好还是时刻留心